A. William Hoglund Papers 1993.0045
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
A. William Hoglund Papers
1868-1997
1993.0045
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
42.9 Linear feet
The collection contains the administrative records of Dr. A. William Hoglund, Professor of History at the University of Connecticut from 1961 until his retirement in 1997.
Biography
Born on September 4, 1926, in Baltimore, Maryland, Arthur William Hoglund spent his childhood on a farm in upper New York state where his parents purchased land with a number of other Finnish immigrants, establishing a community with a strong Finnish American character. After graduating from Spencer High School in Spencer-Van Etten, NY, in 1945 Hoglund studied history at Cornell University, receiving a bachelors degree in 1949. Attending the Univeristy of Wisconsin-Madison for graduate school Hoglund received a master's degree in history in 1950 and a Ph.D in history in 1957. Hoglund's first teaching position was at Muskingum College, in Ohio, from 1957 to 1961, before joining the History Department at the University of Connecticut. Hoglund was appointed Assistant Professor of History at UConn in 1961 and retired as a Professor of History in 1997. A. William Hoglund died in 2008. Hoglund's work was widely published and included books such as Finnish Immigrants in America, 1880-1920 (1960), Union list of Finnish newspapers published by Finns in the United States and Canada, 1876-1985 (1985) and Immigrants and their children in the United States: a bibliography of doctoral dissertations, 1885-1982 (1986).
A detailed biography of A. William Hoglund has been posted by the Finnish North American Literature Association.
Scope and Content
The collection contains administrative records, correspondence, publications, fliers and other materials related to the University of Connecticut's Department of History, and Professor A. William Hoglund's tenure in the department. Subjects discussed in the collection include the UConn; AAUP, UConn Senate, Connecticut State Employees Association, Nutmeg State Employees Credit Union, University of Connecticut Educational Properties Inc., Norwalk Community College, Institute of International and Intercultural Studies, John Hay Fellows of History, Senator Brien McMahon, faculty and administrative staff directories, Harry J. Marks Retirement Committee, UConn's Women's Center, and the Center on Group Life and Intergroup Relations.
The collection also contains a wide selection of academic journals and publications, to include Political Affairs, Science & Society, I.F. Stone’s Weekly, Radical America, Studies on the Left, The Cornell Era, Cornell Review, Trends in Church, Education and Industry Cooperation, Scope, The University of Connecticut Bulletin, The American Review, and The Communist.
Among the many people discussed in the collection are university faculty, to include Albert E. Waugh, Audrey Phillips Beck, Homer D. Babbidge Jr., Christopher Collier, Mary Beth Norton, Paul Goodwin, Reinhold A. Dorwart, Richard D. Brown, Richard O. Curry, Robert Asher, Ronald E. Coons, Karen Kupperman, Hugh M. Hamill Jr., Lawrence Langer, and John A. DiBiaggio.
Provenance and Acquisition
The collection was donated by Dr. Hoglund in several installments beginning in 1993.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students, etc.]. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Additional Hoglund Papers, with a focus on the Finnish American community, are available at the University of Minnesota.
Hoglund, Arthur William, 1926-2008; Administrative Records.; Archives.; Correspondence.; Ephemera.; Financial Records.; Publications.; Universities and colleges--Connecticut--Faculty.; Universities and colleges--Connecticut.
- Series I: Inventory, 1868-1997
  - Administrative records, flyers, publications (newsletter), 1976-1991 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    [Subjects include: UConn AAUP, UConn Senate.]
  - Administrative records, 1973-1988 (Box 2)
    [Subjects include: UConn Senate.]
  - Administrative records, correspondence, 1972-1986 (Box 3)
    [Subjects include: Connecticut State Employees Association, UConn Research Foundation.]
  - Administrative records, correspondence, 1967-1977 (Box 4)
    [Subjects include: University of Connecticut, College of Liberal Arts and Sciences.]
  - Administrative records, correspondence, ephemera, publications (newsletter,), 1966, 1973-1990 (Box 5)
    [Subjects include: Friends of the International Committee (UConn), Nutmeg State Employees Credit Union, UConn Graduate School, UConn Library.]
  - Administrative records, correspondence, ephemera, flyers, Jorgensen, 1962-1991 (Box 6)
    [Subjects include: College of Liberal Arts and Sciences, UConn Graduate School.]
  - Correspondence, ephemera, flyers, publications, 1964-1991 (Box 7)
    [Subjects include: University of Connecticut.]
  - Correspondence, ephemera, flyers, publications, 1981-1992 (Box 8)
  - Administrative records, correspondence, ephemera, financial records, flyers, publications, 1972-1982 (Box 9)
  - Administrative records, correspondence, ephemera, fliers, 1968-1979 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, ephemera, flyers, publications, 1967-1970 (Box 11)
  - Publications, 1980-1992 (Box 12)
    [Subjects include: Graduate course catalog, student handbook,University Calendar, University of Connecticut.]
  - Administrative records, correspondence, ephemera, fliers, publications, 1967-1981 (Box 13)
    [Subjects include: Brien McMahon Lectures, UConn Department of History.]
  - Administrative records, correspondence, ephemera, fliers, publications, 1993-1994 (Box 14)
  - Publications, 1943-1949, 1950, 1964, 1974-1976 (Box 15)
    [Subjects include: Political Affairs, Science & Society.]
  - Administrative records, clippings, correspondence, financial records, publications, 1970-1972, 1983-1987, 1993-1996 (Box 16)
    [Subjects include: Greek life, Office of the Provost, Office of the Registrar.]
  - Publications, 1960-1969, 1972 (Box 17)
    [Subjects include: I.F. Stone’s Weekly, Political Affairs, Radical America, Science & Society, Studies on the Left.]
  - Administrative records, books, clippings, correspondence, ephemera, publications, 1868-1869, 1870-1872, 1951-1956, 1963-1969, 1977, 1983-1984, 1991-1994 (Box 18)
    [Subjects include: Department of History, The Cornell Era.]
  - Administrative records, correspondence, ephemera, notes, 1958-1959, 1960-1961, 1974-1979, 1980-1982, 1990-1995 (Box 19)
    [Subjects include: Department of History, Course catalog.]
  - Publications, 1941- 1949, 1950-1951 (Box 20)
    [Subjects include: Cornell Review, Trends in Church, Education and Industry Cooperation, Scope, The American Review, The Communist.]
  - Administrative records, clippings, correspondence, publications, 1988-1989, 1990, 1992-1997 (Box 21)
    [Subjects include: Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, College of Liberal Arts and Sciences, Department of History.]
  - Administrative records, clippings, correspondence, ephemera, 1963-1964, 1967-1969, 1970-1971, 1974, 1978-1979, 1982, 1990-1997 (Box 22)
    [Subjects include: Student codes and regulations, Department of History, UConn Senate, Viet Report.]
  - Administrative records, correspondence, financial records, notes, 1972-1978, 1985-1989, 1990-1994 (Box 23)
    [Subjects include: College of Liberal Arts and Sciences, Department of History.]
  - Administrative records, correspondence, notes, publications, 1990-1997, 1984-1989 (Box 24)
    [Subjects include: College of Liberal Arts and Sciences, Department of History, Research Foundation, Senate.]
  - Administrative records, clippings, notes, 1965-1967, 1973-1979, 1980-1981 (Box 25)
    [Subjects include: College of Liberal Arts and Sciences, Department of History, AAUP.]
  - Correspondence, ephemera, publications, 1969-1970, 1971-1977, 1980-1987 (Box 26)
  - Administrative records, correspondence, ephemera, publications, 1969, 1970-1979, 1980-1983 (Box 27)
    [Subjects include: Department of History faculty and newsletter.]
  - Administrative records, correspondence, ephemera, notes, publications, 1987-1989, 1990-1993 (Box 28)
    [Subjects include: Mansfield, Department of History.]
  - Clippings, correspondence, ephemera, notes, 1977-1979, 1980-1989, 1990-1996 (Box 29)
  - Administrative records, clippings, correspondence, ephemera, 1977, 1984-1987, 1989, 1991 (Box 30)
  - Clippings, ephemera, manuscripts, notes, 1972-1978, 1987-1989, 1990 (Box 31)
    [Subjects include: Origins of Reformism, Department of History.]
  - Clippings, correspondence, ephemera, publications, 1931-1936, 1951, 1970s (Box 32)
    [Subjects include: I.F. Stone Weekly, University of Connecticut.]
  - Administrative records, correspondence, ephemera, 1960s, 1970s, 1980-1986 (Box 33)
    [Subjects include: Department of History.]
  - Administrative records, clippings, correspondence, ephemera, fliers, notes, posters, publications, transcripts, 1915, 1927, 1940s, 1950s, 1960s, 1970s, 1980-1983, 1992; 1.0 Linear feet Folders with labeled tabs (Box 1993.0045_34)
    Scope and Content Note
    Subjects include: AAUP, Albert E. Waugh, Audrey Phillips Beck, Clarence R. Allen, Dorothy Kenyon, Federation of University Teachers, George B. Cressey, Gustav Arthur Leonard Mehlquist, H. Bentley Glass, Homer D. Babbidge Jr., Jack L. Roach Case, Joel Kupperman, John W. Gray Case, Milton K. Stern, Norman Breyer Case, Norwalk Community College, Paul Weiss, Phi Beta Kappa, Philip E. Taylor, Robert Lekachman, Roy Sieber, S. Fred Singer, University of Connecticut Educational Properties Inc., University of Connecticut Newsletter, University of Connecticut Office of Publications, University of Connecticut student publications, Vermont Royster.
  - Administrative records, clippings, correspondence, ephemera, manuscripts, notes, publications, 1940s, 1950s, 1960s, 1970s, 1980s, 1992, 1994; 1.0 Linear feet Folders with labeled tabs (Box 1993.0045_35)
    Subjects include: Arthur F. Corwin, Benedict V. Maciuika, Christopher Collier, College of Liberal Arts and Sciences, Edmund H. Dickerman, Fred A. Cazel Jr., Graduate School, Harry J. Marks, Herman Mast, History Department, Hugh M. Hamill Jr., Institute of International and Intercultural Studies, Investigation- the Role of the University, James L. McKelvey, John Greene, John Hay Fellows of History, Karen Kupperman, Larry Langer, Mary Beth Norton, Paul Goodwin, placement policy, Proposed Polish Institute, Reinhold A. Dorwart, Richard D. Brown, Richard O. Curry, Robert Asher, Ronald E. Coons, Search Committee for Colonial Position, scholastic standards/requirements.
  - Administrative records, clippings, correspondence, fliers, manuscripts, notes, posters, publications, 1960s, 1970s, 1980s, 1990-1991, 1993-1997; 1.0 Linear feet Folders with labeled tabs (Box 1993.0045_36)
    Subjects include: University of Connecticut History Department.
  - Administrative records, correspondence, ephemera, fliers, notes, posters, publications, 1934-1935, 1939-1941, 1945-1946, 1948-1950, 1961, 1967-1969, 1970s, 1980-1981, 1983-1988; 1.0 Linear feet Folders with labeled tabs (Box 1993.0045_37)
    Subjects include: Center on Group Life and Intergroup Relations, The Chronicle, commencement, Democratic political campaigns, faculty and administrative staff directory, Fraternal Outlook, Graduate Departments, Harry J. Marks Retirement Committee, John A. DiBiaggio, Masses & Mainstream, New Masses, Pipe Dream, Uncensored, The University of Connecticut Bulletin, University of Connecticut Centennial, Voice of Freedom, Women's Center.
  - Publications, 1940, 1942-1943, 1945-1950, 1954-1960, 1964-1968, 1970-1980, 1982-1983; 1.0 Linear feet Some folders with labeled tabs (Box 1993.0045_38)
    Subjects include: The American Review on the Soviet Union, The Bulletin of the United Committee of South-Slavic Americans, The Centennial Review of Arts & Science, Continuity- A Journal of History, The Farm Front, The Harmon Memorial Lectures in Military History, Life Lines, Mainstream- A Literary Quarterly, Marxist Perspectives, Media History Digest, Monthly Review- An Independent Socialist Magazine, New Foundations- A Student Quarterly, New Politics, Political Affairs, Progressive Labor, Radical America, Radical History Review, Rampart Journal of Individualist Thought, Reporter on American Soviet Relations, Science & Society, Studies on the Left, Trends & Tides, U.S.A., Washington Watch, Workers' Opposition.